Good morning. Today's דף daf is י"א. Yud Alef. I want to
start first by mentioning some points from yesterday. We had the whole
discussion about the cutting of the עומר Omer and it overrides שבת,
Shabbos, and then also the possibility that עומר Omer would come from
חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz where the question would be then it would
obviously have to be done a few days before. So I did
want to say that according to the בבלי Bavli actually it's true,
you can't have both things. If you can cut the עומר Omer
before the day itself, it's בדיעבד כשר bedieved kasher before the day
itself, then it wouldn't override שבת, Shabbos, then you would never be
a need to do it on שבת. Shabbos. There is a little
bit of a question about the פסק psak of the רמב"ם Rambam
but anyway I just want to clarify that point. Also, more interestingly,
and this will get us to today's דף, daf, we had ended
yesterday with a list of things that you used the left... the
money from the תרומת הלשכה. Terumat HaLishka. Now an earlier משנה Mishnah
said that the תרומת הלשכה Terumat HaLishka only goes for קרבן ציבור
Korban Tzibur and it does not even presumably go for things that
are... enable קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibur but only actually for the... I'm
sorry, it said only for the קרבן ציבור. Korban Tzibur. It also
did include, I misstated that, it also did include the people that
were watching the grain for the עומר, Omer, so that was some
of the attendant costs for the קרבן ציבור. Korban Tzibur. But anyways
very much with that emphasis on the other hand, the משנה Mishnah
we're dealing with in משנה ב' Mishnah Bet says for example you
could be spend the money on the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah with
the... with the תרומת הלשכה Terumat HaLishka but not on the ramp
that you would make for the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. So it's
really very narrowly defined as the things that are really about the
קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibur itself. That being said, we ended yesterday at
the bottom of י' עמוד ב' Yud Amud Bet with a long
list of things that you would spend the money of the תרומת
הלשכה Terumat HaLishka on which were not the קרבן ציבור. Korban Tzibur.
You would spend it on the rabbinical students that would teach the
כהנים Kohanim the laws of קרבנות. Korbanot. You would spend it on
the שני דייני גזירות, Shnei Dayanei Gzeirot, or some say גזילות, Gzeilot,
to like regular judging in ירושלים Yerushalayim that were on a fixed
salary to regularly be there to deal with various court cases. You
would spend it on... you know, on the women who weaved the
פרוכת. Parochet. What does any of this have to do with קרבן
ציבור? Korban Tzibur? So if you take a look at the הגר"א
Gra here, I should actually mention, I haven't really commented on the
side commentaries, but there are two commentaries here that are based on
the הגר"א. Gra. One is called, if you have the standard וילנא
Vilna printing, one is called the משנת אליהו Mishnat Eliyahu which is
more I think actually transcriptions of his notes, not exactly sure about
that, and the other is תקלין חדתין Taklin Chadashin which means שקלים
חדשים Shekalim Chadashim which is a student of the הגר"א Gra which
also bases him a lot on the הגר"א. Gra. And on the
furthest right margin there is הגהות הגר"א, Haga'ot HaGra, the marginal notes.
So there's three commentaries here based on the הגר"א. Gra. Anyway if
you look at the משנת אליהו Mishnat Eliyahu because one of the
things it said they would spend it on would be on the
מגיהי ספרי העזרה, Magihei Sifrei Ha'Azara, on those that would correct the
ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah or the ספר Sefer in the עזרה, Azara,
whatever that means, and I'll talk about that in a minute. So
if you look at the side here where it says משנת אליהו
Mishnat Eliyahu it says: הכי גרסינן ספר העזרה, Hachi garsinan Sefer Ha'Azara,
ויעוין רש"י בכתובות, v'yeuyen Rashi b'Kesubos, דיבור המתחיל מגיהי ספרים, Dibur Ha'Matchil
Magihei Sfarim, שכל אדם ואדם, she-kol adam ve-adam, דאסור להשהות ספר שאינו
מוגה d'assur lehashot sefer she-eino mugah משום אל תשכן באהליך עולה, mishum
al tishkan be-oholecha avla, that you're not allowed to have an unchecked
ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. So these would be people that would be
hired to basically check people's ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, like you go
to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and you can get your טלית
Tallis and... not טלית, Tallis, your ספר Sefer and מזוזות Mezuzos checked
for free. So you get your ספר תורה Sefer Torah checked, okay
maybe they'd circulate in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And then he says: וראו
בית דין שהיו מתעצלים בדבר, v'rau Beis Din she-hayu mitatzlim badavar, בית
דין Beis Din saw that people were being lazy and not getting
their ספר תורה Sefer Torah checked. People by the way at that
time had ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah just as books of study, not
just for ritual purposes. הפקירו תרומת הלשכה לכך. Hifkiru Terumat HaLishka l'kach.
And they... and they freed up the money of the תרומת הלשכה
Terumat HaLishka for that purpose, which means that on the one hand
it's all about using the money exactly for קרבנות ציבור Korbanot Tzibur
and nothing else. And then we have this long list of all
other things you would use it for, general religious needs which were
not... not even always מקדש Mikdash related and not קרבן ציבור. Korban
Tzibur. And anyway he quotes a רש"י Rashi in כתובות Kesubos that
basically says yeah, the rabbis would stipulate that some of the funds
would go to that, and sort of like retroactively it would never
have been considered sanctified for that purpose. So that's always like a
little trick, a little out, that what the... what the גמרא Gemara
says לב בית דין מתנה, Lev Beis Din Matneh, that בית דין
Beis Din or rabbis or whatever can somehow stipulate at the very
outset we're going to wind up using some of these funds for
this, and we'll say that it was never sanctified you know for
its normally expressed purpose. The other thing, so that helps explain what's
going on about that whole list, why to again to choose those
things as opposed to others is not clear to me. But I
did want to remind you by the way, you know there's a
lot of discussion not what you would use the תרומת הלשכה Terumat
HaLishka for, but also what you would use the שירי הלשכה, Shirei
HaLishka, right? the שירי Shirei of the תרומת הלשכה, Terumat HaLishka, what
was left over once they removed... The three baskets full for the
קרבנות. Korbanot. And if you think about it, and I don't think
we ever stopped to sort of think about this for a moment,
this was the major taxing, you know, money collecting, that they did
of the entire Jewish population, not only in Israel for purposes of
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So the idea that not only by
chance there was like I think normally in my mind I was
thinking, oh, they did it for the קרבנות ציבור, Korbanot Tzibur, but
if there was leftover funds they could use it for the following
things. But if you actually think about it from the very outset
they knew that they were going to collect a lot more funds
than they needed for the קרבנות ציבור Korbanot Tzibur and in a
way this was providing them for some of their operating or regular
funds for the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So the תרומת הלשכה Trumat
HaLishka was we'll remove the amount we need for the קרבנות, Korbanot,
but I don't think it was just by chance, I think from
the outset they knew that there was going to be a lot
of leftover funds and then what were they going to and how
they would use that money. And that's why we read in the
משנה Mishna that they would even use it for like building the
walls of the city, you know, חומת העיר ומגדלותיה משירי הלשכה. Chomat
HaIr u-Migdaloteha mi-Sheirei HaLishka.
So you see that they set aside these things before the end
of the year and they saw that they had a surplus or
they knew what the surplus was, and turned it over for parts
of the year.
Right, there's מותר התרומה Motar HaTruma which is the three baskets and
that money that they're taking from the three baskets and at the
end of the year there's stuff left in those baskets. But that's
the money that was actually used for the תרומת הלשכה. Trumat HaLishka.
Then there's all of the rest of the stuff that they put
a tarp over, right, remember after they took the baskets? And that's
שירי הלשכה Sheirei HaLishka and that would be used for like, you
know, for for fixing the wall of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, like general types
of things.
And there were still
two more תרומת הלשכה Trumat HaLishka exactly because then the new money
because they're constantly collecting money in the year, right, from the more
distant provinces. And that goes on top of the tarp. So all
the money under the tarp which is the money that they already
done the תרומת הלשכה Trumat HaLishka from is the שירי הלשכה Sheirei
HaLishka and that gives them a lot of things that they can
spend it on and I think that, you know, what occurred to
me the other day is that was probably purposeful that they, you
know, or they knew they were going to have all these leftover
funds. I want to spend another minute to also talk about this
fascinating phrase of the what do you call it of the מגיהי
ספר העזרה Magihei Sefer HaAzara or some have the phrase ספר עזרא
Sefer Ezra that עזרא הנביא Ezra HaNavi took. And I just wanted
to introduce you to this famous source, just read it for one
second, it's in אבות דרבי נתן, Avot De-Rabbi Natan, it's also in
the ספרי. Sifrei. In the ספרי Sifrei it's on the פסוק pasuk
in דברים Devarim in וזאת הברכה, Vezot HaBeracha, מעונה אלוהי קדם. Me'ona
Elohei Kedem. Okay, the dwelling place of the god of of of
the ancient God. So here's this here's the passage. ג' ספרים נמצאו
בעזרה. Gimel Sefarim Nimtze'u ba-Azara. Notice again the ספר עזרה, Sefer Azara,
right, three ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah were found in the temple courtyard.
Doesn't say exactly when but presumably at the time of, you know,
who knows, you know, at one time. ספר מעונה, Sefer Me'ona, one
they called the book of מעונה Me'ona because these are all
the variant readings in some of the non... ספר זעטוטי Sefer Za'atuti
והספר היא. ve-ha-Sefer Hi. ספר מעונה, Sefer Me'ona, what does that mean?
באחד היה כתוב מעון אלוהי קדם. Be-echad haya katuv Ma'on Elohei Kedem.
In one it said the מעון Ma'on of God of of the
ancient God. ובאחד היה מעונה U-ve-echad haya Me'ona or and in the
others really it said מעונה Me'ona because there were three so they
took a they did a democracy. Which?
What is the פסוק? pasuk? We have it as מעונה. Me'ona. מעונה
אלוהי קדם ומתחת זרועות עולם ויגרש מפניך אויב ויאמר השמד. Me'ona Elohei
Kedem u-mitachat zero'ot olam vayigaresh mipanecha oyev vayomer hashmied. It's in וזאת
הברכה. Vezot HaBeracha. ביטלו האחד וקיימו השניים. Bitlu ha-echad ve-kiyemu ha-shenayim. So
they said, okay, if two say מעונה Me'ona and one says מעון,
Ma'on, we'll use the מעונה Me'ona גירסא. girsa. So this is a
fame amazing source that it actually says there was some question of
the exact text of the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. אמר רבי יוסי
זה היא ספר שנמצא בבית מעון. Amar Rabbi Yosi, zeh hi sefer
shenimtza be-Veit Ma'on. I have no idea what that
means. ספר זעטוטי. Sefer Za'atuti. באחד היה כתוב זעטוטי בני ישראל. Be-echad
haya katuv Za'atutei Bnei Yisrael. ובשניים היה כתוב וישלח את נערי בני
ישראל. U-vi-shnayim haya katuv vayishlach et na'arei Bnei Yisrael. So instead of
נערי na'arei they had this bizarre word זעטוטי. za'atutei. ביטלו האחד וקיימו
השניים. Bitlu ha-echad ve-kiyemu ha-shenayim. ספר היא, Sefer Hi, the book of
היא. Hi. בכל מקום שהיו כתוב היא היו קוראים הוא. Be-chol makom
she-hayu katuv Hi hayu korim Hu. Right, you know there are times
where it's written with a י' yud and we read it with
a ו'. vav. Like last week we have a lot that it
was written נערה na'ara with a without a ה' heh and we
read it like it was written נער na'ar and we read it
נערה. na'ara. ויש אומרים י"א היא'ס Ve-yesh omrim achad asar Hi's that
there is a question of the גירסא girsa but י"א היא'ס achad
asar Hi's שבתורה. she-ba-Torah. There's a question how many of these
of these different spellings were there? How many היאs Hi were there
that were read הוא? Hu? So one book said eleven times it
was written ה'י'א' Heh-Yud-Aleph and in another ספר sefer there was nine
times it was written ה'י'א' Heh-Yud-Aleph and the other two it was
written ה'ו'א'. Heh-Vav-Aleph. Okay, so it was a spelling issue was it
written with a י' yud or ו'. vav. Everybody read it was
pronounced הוא. hu. ביטלו האחד וקיימו השניים. Bitlu ha-echad ve-kiyemu ha-shenayim. So
this is an amazing source, you know, for for issues about the
text of the תורה Torah and textual variants and if when you
talk about מגיהי ספר העזרה, Magihei Sefer HaAzara, you know, one wonders
here you're correcting ספר העזרה Sefer HaAzara although this was a one-time
thing but maybe it means and this is discussed that they used
the books of the עזרה Azara once they established the text then
they used that to check it against all other or to check
all other ספרי תורה Sifrei Torah against that against that ספר. sefer.
Another interpretation is the book that was read by the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol in the עזרה Azara the ספר
תורה. Sefer Torah. It really sort of parallels this source and might
be referring to this to a similar phenomenon, yes.
With this and with some passages in the בבלי Bavli that have
similar ideas, how is it that people can say that every single
letter is exactly what we have?
Well, it was all there was a mistake and they corrected the
mistakes and it was all the text that they wound up with
was clearly the exact text that they had received. So I don't
know what your problem is Charlie. Okay yes.
This was ostensibly describing a time period prior to the family of
בן אשר Ben Asher and the...
Oh totally, yeah yeah yeah this is prior to the מסורה. Masora.
Yeah the
Masoretes came... מסורה Masora
what was it first second century?
No, later than second century was they? No really? No I thought
it was like fifth or sixth century. Yeah maybe you're right. You
don't have family names that early anyway. I thought I thought it
was in the Geonic period. Yeah yeah yeah. Yes they actually like
recorded every single letter and then they came up with a whole
system to make sure it would be preserved. But this was the
first step in this direction. Alright. So back to the גמרא. Gemara.
So that was a fascinating digression but I wanted to make sure
we had seen that. So bottom here of י"א ע"א Yud Aleph
Amud Aleph we pick up the following.
Again about what the money is going to used for.
Now it says like this... okay. אמר רב חזקיה
תנא
רב יהודה.
Amar Rav Hizkiyah
tana Rav Yehudah. It's right after do you see the last word
on the line with in parentheses about 20 lines up where it
says גרוגרות Grogrot which might have been his name or גודגודות Gudgudot
question what his name was. Okay but anyway רב יהודה Rav Yehudah
said he had a ברייתא. Braita. הקטורת וכל קרבנות הציבור באין מתרומת
הלשכה. HaKetoret vechol Korbanot Hatzibbur ba'in miTrumat HaLishka. The קטורת Ketoret and
all קרבנות הציבור Korbanot Hatzibbur come from the תרומת הלשכה Trumat HaLishka
thank you that's exactly what the shekels supposed to be used for.
מזבח הזהב וכל כלי שרת באין ממותר נסכים, Mizbe'ach HaZahav vechol klei
shareit ba'in miMotar Nesachim, presumably any fixes that they had to make
on the gold altar and all the holy vessels
which were made of gold and silver באין ממותר נסכים, ba'in miMotar
Nesachim, the leftover money from the נסכים, Nesachim, from the wine and
flour that would come with the קרבנות. Korbanot. We're going to see
later today what where that leftover money would come from, what led
to that leftover money. And those leftover funds since נסכים Nesachim are
go totally on the altar and nobody benefits from them, they would
use them also for something that was totally for the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash either the מזבח Mizbe'ach or the כלי שרת. klei shareit.
One wonders how much money they had from the מותר נסכים Motar
Nesachim because it seems like this is a pretty expensive
need here but we'll see what that is we'll see what the
where that money came from in a little bit. מזבח העולה Mizbe'ach
HaOlah the altar for the burnt offering, the outside altar, not the
incense altar, the one in the courtyard, וההיכל והעזרות veHaHeichal veHaAzarot and
any other fixes that they needed for the היכל Heichal which is
the sort of the inner sanctum which is where you had the
מנורה Menorah and the שולחן Shulchan or the עזרות Azarot the outer
courtyard באין משיירי הלשכה. ba'in miShiyarei HaLishka. That would come from the
שיירי הלשכה. Shiyarei HaLishka. שיירי הלשכה Shiyarei HaLishka you had an enormous
amount of latitude we learned in the משנה Mishna you would even
use it for fixing up the walls of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So why
why you use it for this you would think they you could
use more sanctified funds. Well let's read the next line. One minute.
חוץ לעזרות, Chutz laAzarot, if you needed to do fixes on the
temple outside of the עזרה Azara proper, so you're no longer in
the real sanctified space, then באין מלשכת בדק הבית. ba'in miLishkat Bedek
HaBayit. That came from the actually had a fund called the fund
of בדק הבית Bedek HaBayit where people donated money for actual fixing
up the temple proper. So now the question here is that's a
little bizarre if you give money to the בדק הבית Bedek HaBayit
you would assume it would be used in the עזרות Azarot and
in the היכל, Heichal, not in the external. So the גר"א Gra
here points out that the בבלי's Bavli גרסא girsa of this תוספתא
Tosefta of this ברייתא Braita is reversed. It's מזבח העולה וההיכל והעזרות
Mizbe'ach HaOlah veHaHeichal veHaAzarot came from בדק הבית Bedek HaBayit and חוץ
להיכל chutz laHeichal and חוץ לעזרה chutz laAzara came from שיירי הלשכה
Shiyarei HaLishka which makes more sense because the שיירי הלשכה Shiyarei HaLishka
you had a lot of latitude what to do with it. So
he reverses the order here in this ברייתא. Braita.
How was בדק הבית Bedek HaBayit collected? Was that a fix...?
No that was that was just free donations. Free donations?
Free donations to בדק הבית.
Bedek HaBayit. How's that described? Yeah exactly.
Okay so that was free donations בדק הבית. Bedek HaBayit. Why differentiate
between which מזבח? Mizbe'ach?
Yeah that I don't know either I don't know why this מותר
נסכים Motar Nesachim gets this highly specialized function and things that are
like mostly most sanctified and so on. Again other than that it
was totally burnt. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says and also we'll
see anyway. So the גמרא Gemara says like this והתני veha tani
don't we have a ברייתא Braita that says אבני המזבח ההיכל והעזרה
מועלין בהן Avnei haMizbe'ach haHeichal vehaAzarah mo'alin bahem that you can do
מעילה Me'ila with the מזבח Mizbe'ach and the היכל Heichal and the
עזרה? Azara? And based by some ירושלמי's Yerushalmi גרסא... girsa... it says
that that came from שירי הלשכה. shiyarei halishkah. Now, שירי הלשכה, shiyarei
halishkah, after the תרומת הלשכה terumat halishkah was taken, we learned that
the leftover money was desanctified and could be used even to build
the walls of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So if it's desanctified, how are you
doing מעילה Me'ilah with the stuff if you bought the stuff with
it? וכי יש מעילה בשיריים? V'chi yesh me'ilah b'shiyarayim? Is there מעילה
Me'ilah with what's left over from the תרומת הלשכה? terumat halishkah? גמרא
Gemara says אלא כרבי מאיר, ella k'Rabbi Meir, you know what? It's
going like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. ד'רבי מאיר אומר מועלין בשיריים. d'Rabbi
Meir omer mo'alin b'shiyarayim. Yes, remember רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said that
you would still do מעילה Me'ilah on the שיריים shiyarayim because you
might need to draw on those funds if you ran out of
money and you might need to draw on them for the קרבנות.
korbanot. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. אמר רבי חייא, Amar
Rabbi Chiya, כלום אמר רבי מאיר אלא בתוך שנתו. Klom amar Rabbi
Meir ella betoch shnato. When did רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say there
was still קדושה kedushah on the שיריים? shiyarayim? During the year of
that שקל shekel because that was the year that you would draw
on those funds for קרבנות korbanot of that year. והכא חוץ לשנתו
אנן קיימינן. V'hacha chutz l'shnato anan kaymanan.
If that's true, I mean, it's almost like, it's almost like, you
know, you can't win either way. According to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
what would you do with the שירי הלשכה? shiyarei halishkah? You would
leave it untouched so that you might, I mean, he, I don't
know where he'd get his funds for doing everything else, but you'd
leave it untouched because you might run out of money for the
קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibur and you'd have to go back to the
money that was left behind. Okay, but you can only buy the
קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibur this year from the שקל shekel of
this year. So the assumption is that at the end of the
year, then it would become desanctified. Now, I have to tell you,
I don't know how this works, I mean, this קדושה kedushah you
can turn it on and off, right? How the taking of the
תרומת הלשכה terumat halishkah desanctifies the rest? How could רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir at the end of the year when you no longer need
it for that purpose it became desanctified? You somehow have to say
that like the rabbis stipulated from the very beginning that it all
followed the policies and the parameters that they've laid out. So the
גמרא's Gemara question here is one minute, if you want to draw
on those funds for fixing up the מזבח mizbeach or the היכל,
heichal, according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you can't draw on them
during the year, you have to, during the year you have to
have that for the קרבנות. korbanot. So you're only drawing them at
the end of the year. Well, at the end of the year,
after the year's over, we go back to the reality that they
were desanctified. So we're back to our question that if you're using
desanctified funds for the מזבח mizbeach and for the עזרה, azarah, how
do we teach that there is מעילה Me'ilah with those? Okay, so
that's this issue, which is why, by the way, the בבלי's Bavli
answer is much better. The בבלי Bavli reverses the ברייתא Baraita and
says that you buy the מזבח העולה, mizbeach ha'olah, the עזרה azarah
would be from בדק הבית bedek habayit funds, so that would be
sanctified. And the stuff outside the עזרה azarah would be from שירי
הלשכה shiyarei halishkah which would be desanctified and therefore there would not
be מעילה. Me'ilah. But the ירושלמי Yerushalmi that has it in the
reverse is stuck and doesn't understand how you're using שירי הלשכה shiyarei
halishkah and then there still is מעילה. Me'ilah. Yes, Michael?
This word is just a little weird. Like for instance, let's say
I have all my flock of animals. So I take my מעשר,
ma'aser, that's קדוש. kadosh. All the rest of the animals are כחול
חול. k'chul chol. So I could הקדש hikdesh it. Right, the same
thing. So you know, you've all this money and then once you
use, you know, and use a stone that's part of the. I
suppose, I could have,
I suppose it could have said that you could have הקדש hikdesh
it if you wanted to. I mean, I, that's, that's true. I
don't know what, true, it could have said that we, you know,
went ahead and we were הקדש hikdesh it.
Yes, there's another סתם תוספות stam Tosafot that רמב"ם Rambam rules in
accordance with the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and the כסף משנה Kesef Mishneh wonders
why רמב"ם Rambam picked ירושלמי Yerushalmi over the בבלי.
Bavli. Right. So that actually is an interesting thing to say by
the way. First of all, one reason here might be because it's
the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, we also have a general principle like if you
have conflicting סוגיות, sugyot, let's say a סוגיא sugya about I don't
know about שור שנגח את הפרה shor shenagach et haparah and in
בבא קמא Bava Kamma it says one thing and it happens to
be discussed in זבחים Zevachim and says something else, the general rule
is you rule like the בבא קמא סוגיא Bava Kamma sugya because
that's its natural לוקוס. locus. That's where it's really being discussed. So
it could be in שקלים Shekalim is, the רמב"ם Rambam feels you
rule like the ירושלמי Yerushalmi over the בבלי Bavli because there's a
whole ירושלמי Yerushalmi on it. But that being said, while the רמב"ם
Rambam says in his הקדמה למשנה תורה hakdamah l'mishneh torah that we
always go like the בבלי, Bavli, there's been a lot of scholarship
showing where he rules like the ירושלמי Yerushalmi over the בבלי. Bavli.
Like when he felt it was appropriate, he would sometimes have the
בבלי Bavli trump the ירושלמי—the Yerushalmi ירושלמי Yerushalmi trump the בבלי. Bavli.
Anyway, some people used to say that that resolves a lot of
problems in the רמב"ם, Rambam, a lot of contradictions with the בבלי
Bavli is you have to if you appreciate that he's going sometimes
by other rabbinic sources, you know, other Tannaitic sources and the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi and תוספתא Tosefta and so on. Okay, anyway, let's get back
to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, אמר רבי חזקיה, Amar Rabbi Chizkiyah, תני
רבי יהודה גודגדיות Tana Rabbi Yehuda Gudgedayot or גדגדניות, Gadgadniyot, I don't
know, השולחן ha-shulchan same anyway the same אמורא Amora teaches the following
ברייתא. Baraita. השולחן והמנורה והמזבחות והפרוכת מעכבין את הקרבנות. Ha-shulchan v'ha-menorah v'ha-mizbechot
v'ha-parochet me'akvin et ha-korbanot. So we're going to shift a minute from
what you use the money for and talk about what features you
need in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash in order to bring קרבנות.
korbanot. So this says basically you need all of the features that
are in the היכל, heichal, which is interesting. That's not normally where
you bring—you know you bring קרבנות korbanot out in the courtyard. All
of those are מעכבין את הקרבנות. me'akvin et hakorbanos. You can't bring
a קרבן korban without that. But do you need also the ארון
קודש? Aron Kodesh? Not presumably no, they didn't have the ארון קודש
Aron Kodesh in בית שני, Bayis Sheini, so no. I don't know
where they know this from. We're going to have a lot of
statements here which are unsourced. Okay. Now the פרוכת paroches was used
in the הקרבה hakrava of some קרבנות, korbanos, right, of like on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur and so on.
So one of
the מפרשים meforshim says you don't need all of these to bring
an עולה. olah. You need various ones for their various related קרבנות.
korbanos. So to bring the קרבן korban on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
you need the פרוכת. paroches. In order to offer, you know, to
burn the, to do the lighting of the מנורה, menorah, you need
a מנורה. menorah. To do לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim, you need a
שולחן. shulchan. I know. So the simple sense is you need all
of these to be considered to have you have a בית Bayis
in order to bring the קרבנות. korbanos. Okay. Wait, let me just
finish this. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, אין לך מעכב את הקרבן אלא
הכיור והכנו בלבד. ein lecha me'akev et hakorban ella hakiyor vehakano bilvad.
Of all of the things, he said the only thing that's מעכב
me'akev the bringing of קרבנות korbanos is the laver and its base,
the כיור kiyor and the כן. kan. So again, none of this
is sourced, what פסוק pasuk it's based on. The הגר"א, ha'Gra, who
doesn't like this, switches the גרסא girsa to say הכרכוב והקרן, hakarkov
vehakeren, which are features of the מזבח, mizbeach, which means you need
the מזבח העולה mizbe'ach ha'olah with certain of its features in order
to bring it, which makes more sense. But anyway, he switches. I
don't know, because it's based on a בבלי, Bavli, whatever. But anyway,
so I want to remind you that it parallels a discussion in
מגילה Megilla in the בבלי Bavli and other places, which is שמעתי
שמקריבין אף על פי שאין בית. shamati shemakrivin af al pi she'ein
bayis. Okay, that you could be, you could bring a קרבן korban
without there being a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And the question is
like exactly what would you need? I mean, you'd still need a
מזבח mizbeach to bring it on, but that becomes very important around
פסח Pesach time when there people want to go ahead and go
up to הר הבית Har HaBayis and bring a קרבן פסח, korban
Pesach, and you say you don't need a בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
So here it's being discussed, you know, what are the minimum components
that you need in order to be מקריב makriv a קרבן. korban.
Yes. Where were חטאות chata'os and אשמות? ashamos? All animal sacrifices, all
מנחות, minchos, everything was on the outer מזבח. mizbeach. The only thing
that you did on the מזבח הזהב, mizbe'ach hazahav, which was indoors,
let's remember, so you can't have too much smoke or whatever going
on there and too much burning of fats and so on, the
only thing done on the מזבח הזהב mizbe'ach hazahav was קטורת. ketores.
Okay. And sometimes the sprinkling of blood on a, like on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur and
so on. Right. There's also this מזבח העולה. mizbe'ach ha'olah. It's called
מזבח העולה mizbe'ach ha'olah because it's, it means the מזבח mizbeach for
all קרבנות. korbanos. Okay. Yeah, yeah. It's just called מזבח העולה. mizbe'ach
ha'olah. פרוכת paroches divides between the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodoshim. Yes, yes,
but exactly. As were the מנורה menorah and the, right, exactly. And
somehow, according to the first opinion, they were still needed. Okay. So
it says like this, ולא כן אמר רבי אלעזר רבי יוסי בן
חנינה. velo kein amar Rabbi Elazar Rabbi Yose ben Chanina. תריהון אמרין,
terayon amrin, but that, you know, that's really not so, because רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar and רבי יוסי בר חנינה, Rabbi Yose bar Chanina,
they both say, כל היכא דכתיב נוכח מעכב. kol heicha dechtiv nochach
me'akev. Anywhere it says in the תורה Torah נוכח, nochach, I have
no idea what this is based on, it's something that without it
you can't bring קרבנות. korbanos. So for example, by the מנורה menorah
it says ואת המנורה נוכח השלחן. ve'es hamenorah nochach hashulchan. So since
it uses נוכח nochach with the מנורה, menorah, you need that. צלע
אינו מעכב. tzela eino me'akev. If it says צלע, tzela, that's not,
because the שולחן, shulchan, it says you should put the שולחן shulchan
על צלע צפון, al tzela tzafon, on the north side. ואמר רבי
שמואל בר רב נחמן בשם רבי יונתן, ve'amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Rav
Nachman beshem Rabbi Yonasan, ואפילו צלע מעכב. va'afilu tzela me'akev. No, even
where it says צלע, tzela, מעכב. me'akev. ברם אבילא בשם רבי שמואל
בר נחמן, Beram Avilla beshem Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachman, ואפילו שימה מעכב.
va'afilu sima me'akev. Even where it says שימה, sima, you should place
it. Like the ארון Aron and the פרוכת paroches and the מזבח,
mizbeach, וישם. vayasem. He said everything. Pretty much it says it by
everything. I don't know how they would bring קרבנות korbanos in the
בית שני Bayis Sheini because they didn't have an ארון Aron in
the בית שני. Bayis Sheini. Anyway, all of that contradicts this claim
that all you would need would be the כיור kiyor and the
כן. kan. Okay, so how do you resolve that? So אמר רבי
חנינה, Amar Rabbi Chanina, כאן בעבודת שבפנים כאן בעבודת שבחוץ. kan ba'avodas
shebifnim kan ba'avodas shebachutz. So now we're actually saying no, and this
makes sense. If you want to do the stuff on the outer
altar, all of the קרבנות, korbanos, then you just need other than
an altar, then you just need the laver, the כיור kiyor and
the כן. kan. That's what is in the outer space. That's the
only thing you need. If you want to do an inner עבודה,
avoda, like the עבודה avoda on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you know,
like the burning of קטורת ketores and so on, then you need
those various components that we were talking about, the שולחן shulchan and
the מנורה, menorah, etc. I still don't know according to the opinion
that you need the ארון, Aron, how they did any of the
inner עבודות avodos in בית שני. Bayis Sheini. Okay, but anyway, that
resolves the contradiction. Yes. אמר רבי חנינה, Amar Rabbi Chanina, שחצית גדולה
shachatzis gedola הייתה בבני כהנים גדולים, haysa bivnei kohanim gedolim, a great
sort of haughtiness was in the sons of the כהנים גדולים, kohanim
gedolim, and it actually means the כהנים גדולים kohanim gedolim because our
משנה mishna teaches that the כהן גדול kohen gadol would spend their
own funds for building the ramp for the פרה אדומה. parah adumah.
Okay, because that was a very special thing, it happened very rarely,
and they would want it to be their ramp, and they'd spend
their own funds. So, and what does it mean there was a
haughtiness? שיוצא מששים ככר זהב היו מוצאים בה. sheyotzei meshishim kikar zahav
hayu motzim bah. First of all they'd spend more than sixty talents
of gold, some say silver, that's an enormous amount of wealth if
it's gold, they would spend on this ramp, שהיה כבשו של פרה
עומד. shehaya kivsho shel parah omed. First of all, there was already
an existing ramp from the past time they did it, ולא היה
אחד מהן מוציא פרתו בכבש של חברו. velo haya echad mehen motzi
parato bekivsho shel chavero. Nobody wanted to use the ramp that was
used last
time. So אלא סותר ובונה אותו משלו ela soter uvoneh oto mishelo
and build a new one and they'd use you know it was
an enormous amount of expense. So they were very so גאיוועדיק, gaivedik,
it had to be their ramp and they'd be so wasteful. So
התיב רבי עולא קומי רבי מנא. heseiv Rebi Ulla kumei Rebi Mana.
Rebi Ulla asked Rebi Mana, והתני vehatani one minute we have a
ברייתא braita that says
שמעון הצדיק Shimon HaTzadik says
שתי פרות עשה. shetei paros asa. So Shimon HaTzadik in his time,
he lived very long, he was a כהן גדול kohen gadol for
a very long time, they did two פרה אדומות, parah adumos, one
at the beginning of his career and one towards the end. Okay.
So and the end of the ברייתא braita says לא בכבש שהוציא
את זו הוציא את זו. lo bekivesh shehotzi es zo hotzi es
zo. The one that they used for the ramp, the ramp that
they used for the first one wasn't the one they used for
second one. So you see Shimon HaTzadik himself built a separate ramp,
even though presumably it was still around and so on. אית לך
למימר שמעון הצדיק שחץ היה? is lach lemeimar Shimon HaTzadik shachatz haya?
Would you say Shimon HaTzadik was haughty? So it must be that
it wasn't just their own גאווה, gaiva, it must be there was
a real requirement to make a separate ramp. Now you could say
you have to you can make a separate ramp, you don't have
to spend sixty talents of gold on it, but anyway clearly you
see that this was a requirement. Right, dedicated,
so that's for things that are actual קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, you
know, this ramp wasn't even, and we'll talk about that again, right,
we talked about individuals donating like a בגד beged for the בגדי
כהונה, bigdei kehuna, it wasn't the actual קרבן korban proper then you
could do it if you gave it over to the ציבור, tzibur,
and this is something which it was more like, you know, sort
of part of the ritual that the rabbis had developed around the
פרה, parah, it wasn't actually a, you know, something used per se
in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. I don't even think technically this
had to be donated to the ציבור. tzibur. You needed there to
be a ramp, you didn't have to be like a communal ramp.
Well, let's read the answer.
מהי כדו? mai kado? So how do you explain why they made
two ramps, you'd have to make a new one each time? על
שם מעלה היא בפרה סילסול היא בפרה. al shem maala hi baparah
silsul hi baparah. It's a great, it's a, it's a like elevation
that they did by the פרה parah סילסול, silsul, like you have
the phrase מסלסל בשערו, mesalsel bise'aro, like, you know, to sort of
run your fingers through your tresses,
יוסף. Yosef. Anyway, so it's all of these, like, they did all
these special fancy things for the פרה. parah. One of the reasons
is also there was a lot of debates around the פרה אדומה
parah adumah with the צדוקים Tzedukim and so on, so they made,
anyway they made a lot, a big, so anyway, in one area
they were very lenient to to undermine the צדוקים's Tzedukim position so
they went crazy מחמיר machmir in other areas. Anyway, so this is
one of the special things we do and it wasn't just because
of גאווה. gaiva. So תני tani one minute we learned in the
ברייתא braita זיזין וכתלים היו יוצאין מכאן ומכאן zizin uktalim hayu yotzin
mikan umikan in this bridge or ramp that they made, they would
make sure that there were protrusions coming out from it כדי שלא
יצאו ויציצו הכהנים ויטמאו kedei shelo yeitzu veyatzitzu hakohanim veyitamu
because they didn't want everybody hanging off the edge of the of
the bridge and the ramp and looking in and wanting to get
a good sight of the פרה אדומה parah adumah and then they
would, you know, not be careful, they might be טמא, tamei, they
might actually accidentally bring something and touch it. So they needed to
keep everybody away so they made all these protrusions coming out like
a barbed wire, you know, bridge that you couldn't get too close
to.
Ah yes, so we saw we saw רבי עולא Rebi Ulla in
פסחים Psachim in the Yuchsin changes, usually עולא Ulla in the בבלי,
Bavli, right. I can, is there a רבי עולא? Rebi Ulla?
Yeah that's a good point. Presumably I I guess it is always
עולא. Ulla.
That is true. I don't know if it's the same person or
not. Okay רבי עקיבא אומר אין משתכרין. Rebi Akiva omer ein mishtakrin.
Now this was the question of what do you do with if
at the end of the year you have leftover money with the
שירי לשכה. shirei lishka. והשירי לשכה vehashirei lishka remember is the leftover
stuff after you've taken the baskets out. All of that leftover שקלים
shekalim money under the tarp that you know you can now use
for a wide range of purposes for building up the walls of
the city. Now comes the end of the year and ברוך השם
Baruch Hashem you know you have a you have a surplus and
you actually have some leftover funds of the שירי לשכה shirei lishka
which have already been desanctified. What do you do with it? So
רבי ישמעאל Rebi Yishmael says well you buy oil and wine and
flour and you go into business and you sell it to all
the people coming to ירושלים Yerushalayim and pockets the difference makes a
profit. And רבי עקיבא Rebi Akiva says you don't do business with
הקדש hekdesh funds. Okay and then he also you don't do business
with עניים aniyim funds. And the question is is it because it's
inappropriate and it'll raise suspicions and it just looks very like הקדש
hekdesh going into business or is it also the concern that you
know there's risk involved in business and you don't risk funds that
aren't you know that aren't yours to risk. So that would be.
play out in this discussion here in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take
a look. אלא אם רצה Ella Im Ratza says the גמרא, Gemara,
יהא ההפסד שלו ושכר להקדש. Yiheh Ha-Hefsed Shelo Ve-Sechar La-Hekdesh. If you
want to do business with הקדש Hekdesh funds, you can do it
on the stipulation that that if any money is lost, I'll make
up the difference. And I absorb the loss, and so then it's
just protecting the money. But if there's any money to be made,
then that'll go to הקדש. Hekdesh. So if you want to do
that, then you're entitled to which, okay. Now, מותר. Mutar. That's permissible.
כהדא Ka-hada בר זמינא, Bar Zemina, like this בר זמינא, Bar Zemina,
this person בר זמינא, Bar Zemina, איתפקד Itpakad גביה Gabei was entrusted
to him מידל Midal דיתמי. De-yatmi. So מידל Midal is some type
of funds or some have a different גרסא Girsa מלאי Mlai which
is basically anyway
some property of orphans. אתא Ata ושאיל U-she'il לרבי אמי. Le-Rabbi Imi.
He asked Rabbi Imi, can I invest this for the sake of
the orphans? אמר ליה Amar Lei אם בעית Im Bayit דיהא De-yiheh
הפסידא Hefseida דידך Didach if you're willing for the loss to be
yours, ואגרא Ve-agra דתרווייכון De-tarveichon but you'll allow you to split the
profit, then שרי, Shari, it's permissible. So then you're accepting all responsibility
for loss and for your efforts you'll get half the profits, and
but they'll also then you'll invest their funds and they'll get the
profits that allowed. Now some people ask, it's really that makes it
that's almost a type of a ריבית, Ribbit, right? Because basically you
give me money, I promise to get you your money back whatever
happens to the money, okay, which basically makes it like a loan,
okay, but I'm going to use that money and invest it and
and I will take half the profits I'll give you half the
profits. So you're definitely going to get your money back and you
might also get some profit out of it. So isn't that like
a loan with ריבית? Ribbit? So it's not exactly how it's structured,
but it has those qualities. So rabbinically that's generally forbidden, but here
they allowed it for the sake of investing the money of the
orphan.
And this leads into רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva words.
I know, one minute. Okay, one minute. רבי חייא בר אדא Rabbi
Chiya Bar Adda איתפקד Itpakad גביה Gabei מידל Midal דיתמי. De-yatmi. He
also had this, you know, funds of orphans, ועבד כן Ve-avad Kein
and he did the same thing. And I agree that this is
a big חידוש Chiddush because, you know, the simple sense of the
משנה Mishnah אין משתכרין Ein Mishtakrin בשל Be-shel הקדש Hekdesh sounds like
there's something
fundamentally wrong with it, not just that it's too much of a
risk. And it's actually almost a little troubling. Like you understand why
by orphans that, you know, by that's the concern. You don't play
around with other people's money, you know, if it's entrusted to you.
But by הקדש Hekdesh you would think there's more intrinsic concerns as
well. You don't want הקדש Hekdesh going into business, you know, it
does not look good. Whoa, we're collecting all this שקל Shekel for
all of our operating funds and then oh by the way we're
also going into business with some of that money we used and
so on. You know, you don't want to sort of sully the
hands of הקדש Hekdesh with that. But the גמרא Gemara makes it
just about a concern of loss. Okay, now we'll wrap up מותר
פירות. Motar Peirot. Then there was this ambiguous line in the משנה
Mishnah that says the leftover from the fruits, what you would do
with it. So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says what you would do
with it is let me find it
you use it for קיץ המזבח Kayitz Ha-Mizbe'ach which are the עולות
Olot you would bring when the מזבח Mizbe'ach wasn't busy. And it
says רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי חננא סגן הכהנים Rabbi Chanina
Sgan Ha-Kohanim they didn't even refer to מותר פירות Motar Peirot and
it says they didn't agree to it. So what is this מותר
פירות Motar Peirot that they didn't agree to? So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, מתניתין Matnitin רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael היא. Hi.
The משנה Mishnah that talks about the phenomenon of מותר פירות Motar
Peirot is רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. He actually says מותר פירות. Motar
Peirot. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says what you do with it. Why?
ד רבי חייא בר יוסף De-Rabbi Chiya Bar Yosef פתר Patar מתניתא
Matnita the משנה, Mishnah, מותר פירות Motar Peirot שכר להקדש. Sechar La-Hekdesh.
What מותר פירות Motar Peirot is is the money that you made
off of going into business with the wine and the oil. Right?
So the question is: what do you do with the leftover funds
of שירי הלשכה? Shiyarei Ha-Lishka? You go into business with the wine
and the oil according to רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. So what do
you do with that money? What do you do with the profits
from that business? So that he says, oh, that you use for
קיץ המזבח. Kayitz Ha-Mizbe'ach. But now we understand why רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva didn't want to discuss what you do with it because he
didn't agree you were allowed to go into the business to begin
with. Okay. So מותר נסכים Motar Nesachim leftover money from נסכים, Nesachim,
זו סאה רביעית. Zu Se'ah Revi'it.
That is the fourth סאה. Se'ah. What does that mean? It means
that you really want to be very careful before you decide to
be a supplier for the בית המקדש. Beit Ha-Mikdash. On the one
hand it's extremely high volume and you can make a profit, on
the other hand they always have the better of any change and
fluctuation in the market. So you basically stipulated at the beginning of
the year that you will supply them four סאה Se'ah to the
שקל, Shekel, four סאה Se'ah of wine to the שקל. Shekel. And
then the price changes and it's the middle of the year and
now it's going three סאה Se'ah for the שקל. Shekel. Guess what?
You still have to supply them four סאה Se'ah to the שקל.
Shekel. You cannot benefit, you know, you cannot benefit from the price
change, only they can benefit. So if that happens, then they wind
up because then they take that money and they could also resell
it to people that are needing the wine, especially if you hold
sort of like רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael or whatever. Anyway, so
there's other ways as well which I'll get to. So they wind
up with the profit, you know,
during the course of the year. So that's the מותר נסכים, Motar
Nesachim, the way they profit from the fluctuation. What's that called? Not
arbitrage. Is that arbitrage? When you sort of buy in one place,
sell in the other and it fluctuates? Yeah. So they benefit from
the arbitrage and that's the מותר נסכים. Motar Nesachim. זו סאה רביעית.
Zu Se'ah Revi'it. It's like the fourth סאה. Se'ah. סאה se'ah in
that scenario I just drew for you. Anyway so the point is
that מוסר פירות moser peiros is this business and that you went
with the money of שערי אריסקא She'arei Arishka and that's why only
Rabbi Ishmael discussed what you did with it because Rabbi Akiva did
not believe you aren't allowed to use it for that. Rabbi Yochanan
פתר מתניתין patar masnisin this is how Rabbi Yochanan explains the mishnah.
מוסר פירות moser peiros זו סאה רביעית zu se'ah revi'is no, the
מוסר פירות moser peiros is this fourth סאה se'ah the fluctuation the
change in the market price. מוסר נספחם moser nispacham so then what's
the מוסר נספחם? moser nispacham? Okay, so that is לבירוצין. le'beirutzin. בירוצין
Beirutzin is the heaping which basically means like this: if I buy
from you the supplier a gallon or whatever I don't know a
gallon is a gallon a volume measurement? It is, right? I buy
from you a gallon and you fill up your container with a
gallon and you don't get to smooth off the top. Any sort
of
heaping that comes in the container I get even though it winds
up being more than a gallon because I'm the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. All right so again there's going to be a little bit
of a profit then if I go back and then I sell
that wine I'm going to sell it I'm going to smooth off
the top so I'm going to always benefit from that difference. So
that's another way the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash would regularly benefit from
buying and selling wine and that profit that's called מוסר נספחם. moser
nispacham. Now here I have to stop and say you're going to
ask me Rabbi Linzner even Rabbi Akiva agrees to this idea of
מוסר נספחם moser nispacham so aren't you saying it comes from the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash doing business? So and he disagreed with the
whole idea of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash doing business. So here's
the difference, here's the way it worked. What the way it's explained
elsewhere is the following: they didn't exactly do business but
they sort of had like a fixed system up in the following
way. You would walk into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. If you
did not have your נספחם nispacham you would go ahead and stand
in line and pay your say look guy I'm bringing three קרבנות
korbanos today and based on whether they're sheep or whatever they are
they need different נספחם. nispacham. I'm going to need two sheep נספחם
nispacham and one cow נספחם. nispacham. So he says fine here's our
price list ten dollars for the sheep twenty dollars for the cow.
You pay him your whatever your forty bucks and he gives you
three like פתקין p'takin like receipts. Then you walk over to the
נספחם nispacham store you give them the three receipts and they give
you the נספחם. nispacham. So they had it all sort of like
streamlined like that so you would not exactly buy the נספחם nispacham
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash essentially you would because the guy
who gave you the נספחם nispacham he was not working for the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash he was an independent contractor. He took the
receipts he gave you the נספחם nispacham so officially the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash wasn't selling it to you. At the end of the
day he went back to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash he handed
them in the receipts and they reimbursed him. Okay so that's how
the system worked. Even Rabbi Akiva agrees to that. And if again
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is buying it's supplying it's getting the
benefit so in the end when it sort of switches the receipts
for cash it's going to wind up ahead and that's מוסר נספחם.
moser nispacham. And if everybody bringing a קרבן korban pretty much had
to do this that's going back to the משנה mishnah you understand
why there was a lot of money for מוסר נספחם. moser nispacham.
Even if their profit margin was like a half of a percent
but a half of a percent with that volume every single day
they're going to have a lot of money and that's the issue
of מוסר נספחם. moser nispacham. So what Rabbi so the question is
there's two ways either this way of fluctuating prices or of the
way you measured and are those being labeled as two different things
מוסר פירות moser peiros מוסר נספחם moser nispacham or are those being
lumped together because conceptually it's really one thing? It's מוסר נספחם. moser
nispacham. But Rabbi Ishmael said that you could actually go straight into
business selling this stuff and that's what Rabbi Akiva does not agree
to. And now you know why the Galilean rabbi did not like
oil. Right. All right so let's take a look. So it says
like this. So רבי יוחנן פתר מתניתין Rabbi Yochanan patar masnisin מוסר
פירות moser peiros זו סאה רביעית zu se'ah revi'is מוסר נספחם moser
nispacham לבירוצין le'beirutzin the heaping over. So it says דלית ליה לרבי
חייא בר יוסף לבירוצין d'leis lei l'Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef le'beirutzin I
don't get it. Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef he said מוסר פירות moser
peiros was the profit you made according to Rabbi Ishmael the business
and מוסר נספחם moser nispacham was the fluctuation of prices. What about
לבירוצין? le'beirutzin? Why didn't he mention that? So אמר רבי חזקיה מה
דנפל לסאה רביעית נפל לבירוצין. Amar Rabbi Chizkiyah mah d'nafal le'se'ah revi'is
nafal le'beirutzin. No, the same category he put what falls into the
same we talk about it like this it falls into this category.
What falls into the category of the סאה רביעית se'ah revi'is of
the fluctuating prices the בירוצין beirutzin falls into the same category. He
doesn't divide them into two categories. That's all bundled together in מוסר
נספחם. moser nispacham. Okay על דעתיה דרבי חייא בר יוסף ניחא אין
משתכרין בשל הקדש אף לא בשל עניים לפיכך זה וזה לא היו
מודים בפירות. Al da'ateih d'Rabbi Chiya bar Yosef nicha ein mishtakrin b'shel
hekdesh af lo b'shel aniyim l'fichach zeh v'zeh lo hayu modim b'peiros.
So according to Rabbi Chiya we understand why Rabbi Akiva rejected the
whole phenomenon of מוסר פירות moser peiros because Rabbi Akiva said you
don't go into business. And if מוסר פירות moser peiros means the
profit you make from the business then Rabbi Akiva completely rejected it.
על דעתיה דרבי יוחנן קשיא Al da'ateih d'Rabbi Yochanan kashya but according
to... על דעתיה דרבי יוחנן קשיא al daateih derabi yochanan kashya but
according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan why did it say that רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva didn't agree to מוסיף פירות? mosif peirot? Everybody agrees
to this idea of the שער רביעי. sha'ar revi'i. והתנן vehatnan אמדו
מג' יספק מד' amdu migimel yesapek midaled if the price changes to
three for a shekel you still have to continue to supply four.
Okay, ותנינן vetaninan
so everybody agrees to that phenomenon. Now if you're saying מוסיף פירות
mosif peirot means that, not מוסיף פירות mosif peirot means the money
you made from business which רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva didn't agree to
but it means that, that's a phenomenon that everyone agrees to. ותנינן
זה וזה לא היו מודים בפירות vetaninan ze veze lo hayu modim
bepeirot and it says that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רב חנניה
סגן הכהנים Rav Chananya segan hakohanim did not agree with the פירות.
peirot. Why did they not agree? They all agree that this is
a profit the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash made. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, לא היו מודים בפירות לקיצי המזבח. lo hayu modim bepeirot
lekitzei hamizbeach. All it means is they didn't agree to use it
for what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said you used it for. רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said you used it for קיצי המזבח. kitzei hamizbeach.
אבל מודים היו בכלי שרת aval modim hayu bichlei shareit they would
still say you would use it but you'd use it for something
different. You'd use it for כלי שרת klei shareit because מותר נסכים
motar nesachim go to כלי שרת klei shareit like the leftover money
from selling the נסכים nesachim thing with the coupons and what not
the coupons anyway the receipt. And therefore מותר פירות motar peirot is
really a version according to this approach of מותר נסכים. motar nesachim.
It's two forms of מותר נסכים. motar nesachim. So all it means
is they didn't agree they agreed to the phenomenon they didn't agree
to what you used it for. You don't use it for קיצי
המזבח kitzei hamizbeach you use it for כלי שרת. klei shareit. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara ends with a final question about this benefiting
from this heaping: עד כדון בירוצי ציבור ad kadon beirutzei tzibur ואפילו
בירוצי יחיד. veafilu beirutzei yachid. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute
I get how you could use the profits from communal sacrifices. I
it's not exactly clear who's profiting because well I guess you're profiting
from the supplier. You'll have leftover anyway. I get how you could
you could profit when you communal sacrifices you buy a gallon and
you get a little extra than a gallon and then what do
and then what do you do with that profit. So I get
that and then you can use it for these communal purposes like
קיצי המזבח kitzei hamizbeach or כלי שרת. klei shareit. But how about
בירוצי יחיד? beirutzei yachid? Most of their profit was coming from individuals
that brought bought the נסכים nesachim right? And you had all that
profit that they made was coming from individuals from private funds. So
therefore it wasn't ציבור tzibur related. So how could you use it
for the ציבור tzibur purpose of כלי שרת klei shareit or קיצי
המזבח? kitzei hamizbeach? All right it's a good question if that all
that profit is coming now from individual funds not donations but individual
funds. ולא נמצאו כלי שרת באים משל יחיד velo nimtze'u klei shareit
ba'im mishel yachid but then you're winding up buying כלי שרת klei
shareit from individual funds. So the גמרא Gemara says okay big deal.
כהדא דתנינא אשה שעשתה כתונת לבנה kehada detanina ishah she'astah ktonet livnah
כשרה ובלבד שתמסרנה לציבור. ksherah uvilvad shetimserenah latzibur. As long as it's
not the קרבן korban itself you can have an individual donate something
as long as once they donate it they fully give it over
to the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So if I'm buying wine and
I'm paying then I'm fully giving it over to the בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash right? So I'm not making it a private thing and
therefore that can then go ahead and be used for these more
communal purposes. One last question about this: עד כדון בירוצי לח. ad
kadon beirutzei lach. We get that you benefit from the heaping of
a liquid measure. בירוצי יבש beirutzei yavesh how about if it's a
dry measure? Now why should it be different? So one explanation of
why it's different is because one of the reasons that בית דין
Beit Din is entitled to the heaping over is because when you
pour the liquid in it hits the inside of the כלי keli
the כלי keli is קדוש kadosh that sanctifies it. And then as
you keep on pouring stuff that's already been in the כלי keli
you know winds up stuff moves around. The heaping stuff is not
just the stuff you poured last. So that stuff has already been
קדוש kadosh it was once in the כלי keli and therefore we're
entitled to it because it's been sanctified. Whereas if it's a dry
measure the heaping part of it was never inside of the כלי
keli right? Because right if you put in grain into a box
the grain that heaps over was never inside the כלי. keli.
Well maybe it touches the כלי keli okay but it wasn't
in the walls of the כלי keli and the walls of the
כלי keli is what קדוש. kadosh. It wasn't even in the air
space but the air space above the כלי keli not the air
space of the כלי. keli.
So the גמרא Gemara wanted to talk about the meniscus.
Yes the meniscus I that's the word I was thinking about. Right
I was trying to remember. So there the liquid started in the
כלי keli but by dry it didn't. So are we entitled to
the heaping of the dry measures as well? Okay כהיא דתנינא kehi
detanina
like we taught over there: הנסכים שקידשו בכלי ונמצא הזבח פסול. hanesachim
shekidshu bichli venimtza hazevach pasul.
So you sanctified the נסכים nesachim in a vessel and then the
then the קרבן korban was פסול pasul and so you can't use
the נסכים. nesachim. אם יש שם זבח אחר יקרבו עמו im yesh
sham zevach acher yikrevu imo
if there's another קרבן korban then you use it for that. ואם
לאו veim lav ואם לאו veim lav and if not ללנו lelanu
so if they stayed over the night יפסלו בלינה. yipaslu belinah. Now
what the heck does that tell us? Doesn't seem to tell us
anything about this question. So the גרא Gra says the end of
that גירסא girsa what the the גרא Gra tells us that again
that in the תוספתא Tosefta I believe the end of that text
is let me see again what the גרא Gra has. He says
the end of the text is ואם לאו ימכרו לקיצי המזבח. veim
lav yimcheru lekitzei hamizbeach. That the end of the text says and
if if you didn't And since it speaks about נסכים nesachim generically,
it would also include, you know, the
dry נסכים nesachim that they would go look the קיץ המזבח. Keitz
HaMizbeach. Now again, it's still not exactly clear how does that relate
to the heaping part, right? Where do you see the sense of
the heaping part here? So there's a lot of playing around with
the גירסא girsa to make this make sense, but for now, because
of, particularly because of time and because it's complicated and not so
convincing, we will leave it with that question. Okay, so let's take
a look now at the next משנה. Mishnah. מותר הקטורת, Motar HaKetoret,
what would you do with the leftover קטורת? Ketoret? Now, what leftover
קטורת? Ketoret? So every year they would buy at the beginning of
the year, for whatever reason this was the practice, 365 units of
קטורת, Ketoret, מנה'ס, manas, they would use one unit each day and
plus three extra they would use on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, 368.
The problem is is that a lunar year, since they renewed the
שקלים Shekalim on a lunar year basis, was did not have 365
days. Now, if you collect the excess of the קטורת Ketoret over
a few years, then you'll have if you can use it when
you have a leap year, right? Over three years you collect the
excess of the difference of lunar and solar and then when you
get the leap year then you can use it. But there's a
problem: you have to buy a קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibur of that
year from that year's funds. So once they had this weird practice
of starting with 365 plus three, how did they use the leftover
קטורת Ketoret that they had in order to get it to be
repurchased with הקדש Hekdesh funds for the next year? Okay, that's the
question. So how would they do it? מותר הקטורת מה היו עושים
בה, Motar HaKetoret mah hayu osim bah, what would they do? מפרישין
ממנו שכר האומנין, mafrishin mimenu sechar ha'umnin, you separate out from it
the money you owed for the workers, the people that actually would
make the קטורת, Ketoret, ומחללין אותו על מעות האומנין, umechalelin oto al
me'ot ha'umnin, you transfer the קדושה kedusha of the קטורת, Ketoret, the
leftover let's say 10-11 מנה'ס manas that you would have at the
end of the year, to the money that you owed the אומנין.
umnin. Okay, and then you had desanctified קטורת, Ketoret, and then what
you would do with it? ולוקחין אותה מתרומה חדשה, velokechin otah mitrumah
chadashah, and then you'd repurchase it from the new funds and then
it would be resanctified with this year's funds. Okay, ואם בא חדש
בזמנו לוקחין אותה מתרומה חדשה, ve'im ba chadash bizmano lokechin otah mitrumah
chadashah, and now which funds would you use? So if the new
funds, the new שקלים Shekalim are ready to be used, you'd buy
it with the new שקלים. Shekalim. ואם לאו מן הישנה, ve'im lav
min hayeshanah, and if not you'd buy it with the old שקלים,
Shekalim, which sort of begs the question: the whole idea was to
get it to be repurchased with this year's funds, what does it
mean that if you didn't have this year's funds you'd repurchase it
with the old funds and then what's the point of this whole
exercise? Okay, so we'll talk about that, but let's first focus on
the קטורת Ketoret question. So what you all should be asking me
is whoa, whoa, what did you do? You transferred the קדושה kedusha
of קטורת Ketoret to the money that you're going to pay the
אומנין? umnin? Then I've got a little bit of a question, which
is what? What are the אומנין umnin going to do with money
that's sanctified? Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
The אומנין umnin were כהנים?
Kohanim? Again, all these people were כהנים? Kohanim?
What? Priest... yeah, it's not necessarily, but in practice yes.
And but the קטורת Ketoret is made in the מקדש? Mikdash?
Oh, we're going to discuss that, where it's made. We're going to
discuss how these where these אומנין umnin are and so on, don't
worry.
But it is purchased in
other words so you have
this בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash sounds like a mall.
Okay, let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. ולא נמצא הקדש מתחלל על
ההקדש? vilo nimtza hekdesh mitchalel al ha'hekdesh? Wait a minute, isn't הקדש
hekdesh now transferred on הקדש? hekdesh? Now that's a little funny. There's
another גירסא girsa which is better, which is ולא נמצא הקדש מתחלל
על המלאכה, vilo nimtza hekdesh mitchalel al hamelachah, meaning how can you
use the money to pay the אומנין, umnin, where is the קדושה
kedusha going, on the work that they did? The work is an
abstraction, right? So where is the sanctity of the money going if
you're paying it to the אומנין? umnin? So כיצד הוא עושה, keitzad
hu oseh, here's how you do it. What would you do? אמר
רבי סימון בן בסנא, amar Rabi Simon ben Bisna, מביא מעות ומחללן
על הבנין. mevi me'ot u'mechalelan al habinyan. Here's what you do: you
bring your money, here's my money that I'm going to pay, my
sanctified money that I'm going to use my $100 that I'm going
to use to pay the אומנין, umnin, but it's sanctified. First thing
I do is here, and this will be the קטורת Ketoret that
they have, they're coming to me and they say, here you are
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, here's the קטורת Ketoret we worked on, okay,
and this is the leftover קטורת Ketoret that we worked on. Now
it's still owned by the אומנין, umnin, they've used their own funds
to do it, they put in the work, they own the קטורת,
Ketoret, and the קטורת Ketoret is now worth all of the original
cost of the ingredients plus all of the work that they put
into it. Here's the קטורת, Ketoret, that's they're coming and they want
to be paid, okay. I have the money that's their pay, which
is both for their work and for the ingredients that they used.
I have their money, this is sanctified money. What do I do?
מחללן על הבנין, mechalelan al habinyan, I transfer the קדושה kedusha of
this money to I don't know the bricks over there that I'm
going to use later for the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So I
make this money desanctified. I don't know why it didn't just say
I start with desanctified funds, but okay, let's keep on going.
ומביא קטורת, umevi ketoret, now I've got this קטורת Ketoret that the
אומנין umnin have brought me, ומחלל אותה עליהן, umechalel otah aleihen, and
I transfer the קדושה kedusha of this קטורת... Ketoret... onto this money.
Okay, that's all very lovely, but we're back to square one. How
am I paying the אומנים? omnim? Okay, so here's the twist. I
like, why you needed the first half is unclear. You transfer the
קדושה kedusha of the קטורת k'tores on it, but here's how you
pay the
אומנים. omnim. ונותנין אותה לאומנין בשכרן. venotnin osa l'omnim bischaran. You pay
them with the קטורת. k'tores. Okay, basically, they come to me and
they say, here's the, you know what it's like? It's like imagine
you go to a restaurant, right? So the raw ingredients are very
little, but you're paying $50 for the meal because it's all the
effort whatever. So they come to you and they say, here's the
meal, like the אומנים omnim say, here's the קטורת k'tores we just
did, that'll be $50, and you say, you know what? I don't
have the money on me here. Here's something worth $50, and you
give them the meal right back. Okay, so that's what happens. The
אומנים omnim deliver to you the קטורת k'tores sanctified, you de-sanctify it,
you give them back the קטורת k'tores for their pay. Okay, but
we're not done, because now, okay, לאומנין בשכרן, l'omnim bischaran, and then
what do you do? Now, but actually, I just gave you that
קטורת, k'tores, but I need that קטורת k'tores for this coming year!
So then I will buy that קטורת k'tores with sanctified funds, but
the sanctity now will transfer to the קטורת k'tores and you'll get
the money that you want. Okay, do you get it? So they
basically they come and they serve me my $50 dinner, okay, I
say I don't have the money, here's the dinner back for payment,
and then I say, wait wait, I'll buy the dinner from you
for 50 bucks. But the whole reason of this is it gets
the קדושה kedusha off of the קטורת. k'tores. So you de-sanctify the
קטורת, k'tores, you pay them with the קטורת, k'tores, then you buy
the קטורת k'tores with sanctified funds and that transfers the new קדושה
kedusha onto the קטורת. k'tores. Okay, ונותנין אותה לאומנין בשכרן, venotnin osa
l'omnim bischaran, yes? Exactly. And the coins you give them becomes de-sanctified.
The קטורת k'tores becomes de-sanctified, then you use sanctified funds from the
new שקל shekel to buy it, and the sanctity they get the
money and the sanctity of the money transfers to the קטורת. k'tores.
And the money is no longer sanctified.
Exactly. And then they can use the money. Okay. All right. Now,
אותן המעות מה יעשה בהן? osan hamaos ma ya'aseh bahen? Now this
money that had the קדושה kedusha of the קטורת k'tores transferred to
it, okay, I'm sorry, this money that was, excuse me, that was
what's money is left over now?
Hold on.
What is it used to?
Yeah, but that's the one that went to...
No, the קדושה kedusha is now on the קטורת. k'tores. You still
have the money for this קדושה. kedusha.
Oh,
no no no, you're right, you're right, you're right, there's two sets
of money. Right, right, there's two sets of money. First you transfer
the קדושה kedusha off of the קטורת k'tores to one set of
money, but then you bought back the קדושה kedusha with the new
שקל, shekel, right? So what do you do with the money that
you transferred the קדושה kedusha of קטורת k'tores the first round onto,
right? Right. How does the קדושה, kedusha, exactly, what do you do
with that money that has the קדושה kedusha of the קטורת? k'tores?
So רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, אומר אני, omer ani, I say, יינתנו
לבית גרמו ולבית אבטינס, yinatnu l'veis Garmo u'l'veis Avtinas, שהיו בקיאין בפיטום
הקטורת ובמעשה לחם הפנים. shehayu beki'in b'pitum hak'tores u'v'ma'aseh lechem hapanim. Basically,
you give this to the house of Garmo that would basically, you
know, regularly do this work for the קטורת k'tores and לחם הפנים,
lechem hapanim, which is not clear, first of all what are they
going to do with הקדש hekdesh funds, and second of all don't
they get generally paid anyway? So אמר רבי שמואל בר רב יצחק,
Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak, והן שהיו חייבין להם מעות משנה
ראשונה. v'hen shehayu chayavin lahem ma'os mishana rishona. That's only if you
basically, the way the מפרשים mefarshim say this, if you owe them
money from a previous year, because this has the קדושה kedusha of
the קטורת k'tores from last year. So then you're using last year's
funds. Now remember, now it makes sense because we talked at the
bottom at the עמוד ב amud beis yesterday that you could use
the תרומת הלשכה terumas halishka for some of these types of, like
you know, of services that weren't just קרבנות ציבור. korbanos tzibur. So
the last year's קטורת, k'tores, the קדושה kedusha was transferred to this
money, okay, it has last year's קדושה kedusha of the שקל. shekel.
You can actually use that קדושה kedusha of the שקל shekel of
last year to pay for some of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
services, so you pay it. But that's only if you're paying for
last year's services, because this has last year's קדושה kedusha on it.
Okay? Because they're allowed to have these de-sanctified funds then? What?
You're allowed to have these? No, then the funds become de-sanctified. That's
one of the uses, like it's paying the מגיהי ספרים, magihei s'farim,
paying the rabbinic students, right, we just taught that, right? We just
began with that today, that you can wind up using the תרומת
הלשכה terumas halishka for more non-קדושה kedusha purposes and then it becomes
or something? Yeah, then חז"ל Chazal just stipulate and make it non-קדוש.
kadosh. I mean, that's the bizarre thing of all of it. Okay.
What? It's one mentioned. I know. אמר רבי בא בשם רבי חייא
בשם רבי יוסי: Amar Rabbi Ba b'shem Rabbi Chiya b'shem Rabbi Yosi:
No, that's not what you would do with it, not to pay
off something from last year's funds, but you use the general fallback
מקיצין בהן את המזבח. m'kitzin bahen es hamizbe'ach. You'd use it to
bring these עולות olos for when the מזבח mizbe'ach is not being
used. Okay. Let's just do one more issue. רבי בא בר כהנא
בעי, Rabbi Ba bar Kahana ba'ei, he asks the following question, קומי
רבי יוסי, kumei Rabbi Yosi, מחלפא שיטתיה דרבי חייא בר בא. machalfa
shittatei d'Rabbi Chiya bar Ba. Rabbi Chiya bar Ba is reversing himself.
תמן צריכה ליה, Taman tzricha leh, first Rabbi Chiya bar Ba said,
what do you do with these funds? והכא פשיטא ליה, V'hacha peshita
leh, and then at the end of the discussion he said, oh,
you use it for קיץ המזבח. kayitz hamizbe'ach. How did he ask
a question and then give the answer to his own question? I
don't know why he has such an issue. No, הגמרא hag'mora says
צריכא ליה בכלי שרת, tzricha lei biklei shareit, הא דפשיטא ליה בקיץ
המזבח. ha depshita lei bekeytz hamizbeach. When he said what do you
do with the funds, he meant I know you can always do
the fallback of קיץ המזבח. keytz hamizbeach. What I'd like to know
is can you also use it for כלי שרת? keli shareit? And
that he didn't have an answer for. Okay, but that's how you
end this whole process with the קטורת. ketoret. This פלגא, palga, now
that the גמרא Gemara says there is a debate on the following,
and this is Rabbi Dov's question: פיטמה בחולין, pitma bechulin, let's say
you ground the קטורת ketoret in a non-sanctified vessel. Can you make
קטורת ketoret unsanctified and sanctify it afterwards? So רבי יוסי בר רבי
חנינא Rebbi Yossi bar Rebbi Chanina אמר פסולה, amar psula, it's invalid.
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rebbi Yehoshua ben Levi אמר כשרה, amar ksheira,
it's kosher. Now מה טעמא דרבי יוסי בר רבי חנינא? ma taama
de-Rebbi Yossi bar Rebbi Chanina? קודש היא, kodesh hi, it says by
the קטורת, ketoret, it is holy. שתהא הוייתה בקודש, she-te-he havayata bakodesh,
its very making has to be in something sanctified; its very making
has to be in a sanctified vessel. מה טעמא דרבי יהושע בן
לוי? ma taama de-Rebbi Yehoshua ben Levi? What's the reason of רבי
יהושע בן לוי? Rebbi Yehoshua ben Levi? קודש היא kodesh hi שתהא
באה מתרומת הלשכה. she-te-he ba-ah mitrumat halishka. קודש kodesh just means it
has to be bought from קודש kodesh funds; it does not have
to be made in a כלי
שרת. keli shareit. אמר רבי יוסי ברבי בון, amar Rebbi Yossi berebbi
Bun, אתיא דרבי יוסי בן חננא כשמואל, atya de-Rebbi Yossi ben Chanana
k-Shmuel, דרבי יהושע בן לוי כרבי יוחנן. de-Rebbi Yehoshua ben Levi k-Rebbi
Yochanan. They have various supports for their positions. We'll just read the
first one and end there, דתנינא de-tanina because this is our
משנה, Mishnah, המקדיש נכסיו ha-makdish nechasav והיו בהם, ve-hayu bahem, you know
what? I think we have to end here. So we will pick
up with this today tomorrow.